<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lescobedop.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://lescobedop.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-07-20T15:58:43+00:00</updated><id>https://lescobedop.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">All things change when we do</title><link href="https://lescobedop.github.io/blog/2025/On-Change/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All things change when we do" /><published>2025-07-18T08:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-18T08:45:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lescobedop.github.io/blog/2025/On-Change</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lescobedop.github.io/blog/2025/On-Change/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>All Things Change When We Do</strong></p>

<p>We often perceive change as something that arrives from the outside—unexpected, uninvited, disruptive. Yet the most enduring transformations begin within. The world doesn’t shift simply because we observe it; it shifts, almost imperceptibly, as <strong>we ourselves are reshaped</strong>. These subtle internal recalibrations—deliberate and profound—begin to inform how we see, how we choose, and how we lead.</p>

<p>Robert J. Anderson and William A. Adams put it plainly in <em>Mastering Leadership</em>: <strong>identity forms the lens through which we comprehend the world</strong>. More than circumstance, it is our <em>inner structure</em> that shapes how we engage, respond, and ultimately evolve.</p>

<p>My own journey as an immigrant brought this into sharp focus early. Leaving home felt like <em>liberation</em>—a border crossed, a future imagined, a horizon stretched open. What I hadn’t grasped was that <strong>access grants entry, not liberty</strong>. For all the beauty I encountered, a quiet tension lingered beneath it.</p>

<p>Living across countries expands one’s perspective, revealing that what we once called universal is often merely local custom. The “right way” becomes relative. Even as that awareness matures, another truth emerges: for those navigating new languages, laws, and expectations, freedom is rarely absolute. Legal documentation offers structure, not certainty. We adapt to shifting policies, invisible norms, and the quiet hierarchies of belonging. Even the communities around us—warm and well-meaning—can subtly shape the boundaries of our perceived legitimacy. In time, I realized: <strong>seeing the world isn’t the same as moving freely within it</strong>.</p>

<p>Yet it was within those constraints that a deeper clarity took shape. <strong>Freedom, I came to understand, isn’t the absence of barriers—it’s the quiet strength to transcend them</strong>. This isn’t about escape, but about <em>becoming</em>. It’s in naming the limits that we learn how to rise above them—not only for ourselves, but in ways that allow others to do the same. As Marianne Williamson reminds us, “As we let our own light shine, we unconsciously give other people permission to do the same.”</p>

<p>Even fear began to take on new contours. I came to see it not as a signal to retreat, but as an <em>invitation to examine</em>. Its shape varied from place to place, its voice shifting with culture. What once felt like danger became, in the right context, a <em>threshold</em>. This wasn’t a call for recklessness—it was the slow cultivation of <em>discernment</em>. I no longer mistook the unfamiliar for the unsafe.</p>

<p>Education refined this perception further. Not merely as formal instruction, but as a broadening of one’s <em>field of vision</em>. The more I studied, the more I saw—not just in the world, but in myself. Learning sharpened the questions I asked of the world and <em>of myself</em>. Slowly, what once passed unnoticed revealed itself with quiet insistence.</p>

<p>With time, this inner expansion reshaped how I moved through the world. My decisions became more deliberate. My cadence steadied. Clarity took the place of urgency. What once demanded force now responded to <em>rhythm</em>. Leadership became less a matter of visibility and more one of <em>presence</em>—less about momentum, more about <em>meaning</em>.</p>

<p>The insight endures: <strong>all things change when we do</strong>. The world does not bend to our desires. It reveals itself in response to <em>who we are becoming</em>. And so, the work is always close to home.</p>

<p>This, I believe, is the true <em>architecture of transformation</em>—<strong>built in clarity, refined through deliberate action</strong>. The most lasting change does not begin with the world; it begins with the self. That is the highest form of <strong>agency, and the most enduring power we will ever possess</strong>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflections" /><category term="change" /><category term="identity" /><category term="growth" /><category term="mindset" /><category term="leadership" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A personal reflection on change, identity, and the quiet power of internal transformation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From solitude to strength: on having a personal den</title><link href="https://lescobedop.github.io/blog/2025/The_Wolfs_Den/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From solitude to strength: on having a personal den" /><published>2025-05-06T06:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-06T06:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://lescobedop.github.io/blog/2025/The_Wolfs_Den</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lescobedop.github.io/blog/2025/The_Wolfs_Den/"><![CDATA[<p>All my life, I have found myself drawn to <strong>wolves</strong>. Not merely the creature of the wild, but the potent <strong>archetype</strong> they embody—that compelling blend of loyalty, intrinsic family bonds, formidable ferocity, and unerring precision. These <strong>tenets</strong> have, in many ways, guided my path for as long as I can recall, shaping my approach to life with a <strong>quiet consistency</strong>.</p>

<p>While inherently gregarious, I have never been one for multitudes. My associations—whether from formative years, professional endeavors, or life itself—have been few, yet <strong>carefully cultivated</strong>. These individuals, through shared experience, became my <strong>nascent pack</strong>. Their presence lent both rhythm and vital energy to my early days.</p>

<p>And yet, even then, I found profound solace in <strong>solitude</strong>. I would readily dedicate entire days to it—not born of melancholy, nor avoidance, but from an undeniable need for stillness, a duration unburdened by distraction. In those contemplative hours, I engaged with musical composition, immersed myself in study, explored the canvas, and put pen to paper. I was not retreating from the world; rather, I was <strong>stepping more deeply into myself</strong>.</p>

<p>My mother, observing this inclination, would often refer to my room as my <em>fortress of solitude</em>. I confess, I took it as a playful nod to a certain heroic figure. Years later, however, she confided her quiet concern—fearing I might be grappling with unexpressed difficulties, suffering in silence.</p>

<p>Her apprehension was not entirely unfounded in its sentiment, though her interpretation missed the mark. There was no turmoil; rather, a <strong>profound sense of discovery</strong>. In solitude, I did not unravel. I <strong>assembled</strong>. I <strong>discerned</strong> my core motivations. I perceived underlying patterns. I <strong>forged resilient systems</strong>. I <strong>mastered my own internal cadence</strong>. This essential truth has remained unchanged.</p>

<p>Even today, my most fruitful moments are found in <strong>deliberate focus</strong>. Not isolation, mind you—but <strong>intentional internal space</strong>. That, I believe, is the <strong>crucial distinction</strong>. This is no fortress of retreat; I am not withdrawing from the world. I am, instead, <strong>refining within it</strong>.</p>

<p>Now, as I am privileged to have a family of my own, I still cultivate this <strong>inner clarity</strong>—often with their <strong>vibrant presence</strong> nearby. My wife and son, a <strong>source of boundless energy</strong>, are not a distraction from the work; they are, unequivocally, the <strong>profound reason</strong> for it.</p>

<p>This, then, is no longer mere solitude. This is <strong>The Wolf’s Den</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>The Wolf’s Den</strong> is a place imbued with <strong>clarity</strong> and <strong>memory</strong>. It is a <strong>crucible for sharpening</strong> and a <strong>sanctuary for family</strong>.</p>

<p>It is a space where I can reflect, cultivate growth, and articulate thoughts freely—not out of a need for isolation, but from an intimate understanding of who I am.</p>

<p>And when I re-engage with the world beyond its walls, it is with a heightened sense of <strong>strength</strong>, never diminished. For while wolves are powerful alone, they are truly <strong>unstoppable in a pack</strong>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflections" /><category term="identity" /><category term="solitude" /><category term="mindset" /><category term="legacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on solitude, identity, and the purpose behind The Wolf's Den.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From solitude to strength: on having a personal den</title><link href="https://lescobedop.github.io/blog/2025/sample-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From solitude to strength: on having a personal den" /><published>2025-05-06T06:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-06T06:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://lescobedop.github.io/blog/2025/sample-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lescobedop.github.io/blog/2025/sample-post/"><![CDATA[<p>All my life, I have found myself drawn to <strong>wolves</strong>. Not merely the creature of the wild, but the potent <strong>archetype</strong> they embody—that compelling blend of loyalty, intrinsic family bonds, formidable ferocity, and unerring precision. These <strong>tenets</strong> have, in many ways, guided my path for as long as I can recall, shaping my approach to life with a <strong>quiet consistency</strong>.</p>

<p>While inherently gregarious, I have never been one for multitudes. My associations—whether from formative years, professional endeavors, or life itself—have been few, yet <strong>carefully cultivated</strong>. These individuals, through shared experience, became my <strong>nascent pack</strong>. Their presence lent both rhythm and vital energy to my early days.</p>

<p>And yet, even then, I found profound solace in <strong>solitude</strong>. I would readily dedicate entire days to it—not born of melancholy, nor avoidance, but from an undeniable need for stillness, a duration unburdened by distraction. In those contemplative hours, I engaged with musical composition, immersed myself in study, explored the canvas, and put pen to paper. I was not retreating from the world; rather, I was <strong>stepping more deeply into myself</strong>.</p>

<p>My mother, observing this inclination, would often refer to my room as my <em>fortress of solitude</em>. I confess, I took it as a playful nod to a certain heroic figure. Years later, however, she confided her quiet concern—fearing I might be grappling with unexpressed difficulties, suffering in silence.</p>

<p>Her apprehension was not entirely unfounded in its sentiment, though her interpretation missed the mark. There was no turmoil; rather, a <strong>profound sense of discovery</strong>. In solitude, I did not unravel. I <strong>assembled</strong>. I <strong>discerned</strong> my core motivations. I perceived underlying patterns. I <strong>forged resilient systems</strong>. I <strong>mastered my own internal cadence</strong>. This essential truth has remained unchanged.</p>

<p>Even today, my most fruitful moments are found in <strong>deliberate focus</strong>. Not isolation, mind you—but <strong>intentional internal space</strong>. That, I believe, is the <strong>crucial distinction</strong>. This is no fortress of retreat; I am not withdrawing from the world. I am, instead, <strong>refining within it</strong>.</p>

<p>Now, as I am privileged to have a family of my own, I still cultivate this <strong>inner clarity</strong>—often with their <strong>vibrant presence</strong> nearby. My wife and son, a <strong>source of boundless energy</strong>, are not a distraction from the work; they are, unequivocally, the <strong>profound reason</strong> for it.</p>

<p>This, then, is no longer mere solitude. This is <strong>The Wolf’s Den</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>The Wolf’s Den</strong> is a place imbued with <strong>clarity</strong> and <strong>memory</strong>. It is a <strong>crucible for sharpening</strong> and a <strong>sanctuary for family</strong>.</p>

<p>It is a space where I can reflect, cultivate growth, and articulate thoughts freely—not out of a need for isolation, but from an intimate understanding of who I am.</p>

<p>And when I re-engage with the world beyond its walls, it is with a heightened sense of <strong>strength</strong>, never diminished. For while wolves are powerful alone, they are truly <strong>unstoppable in a pack</strong>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflections" /><category term="identity" /><category term="solitude" /><category term="mindset" /><category term="legacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on solitude, identity, and the purpose behind The Wolf's Den.]]></summary></entry></feed>